(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-09-02T01:19:08.785736",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.6-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
皆さん、こんばんは！ハロー！
Good evening, everyone! Hello!
こんばんは！
Good evening!
はい！ということで、まずは自己紹介からやっていきましょう！
Alright! First off, let's introduce ourselves!
ホロライブの清楚担当、みんなのアイドル夏色まつりです！
I'm Natsuiro Matsuri, Hololive's pure and wholesome idol!
今日はMCを担当します。頑張ります！
I'll be your host today. I'll do my best!
じゃあ今日参加してくださる人たち1人ずつ行きますよ。
Next, let's have everyone introduce themselves one by one.
じゃあ、イオフィからお願いします！
Let me hand it over to Iofi first!
はい！イフォリア・オビサ！どうもです！
Hi! Ioforia obisa! Hello!
ホロライブインドネシアからイオフィです！
I'm Airani Iofi from Hololive Indonesia!
今日はオノマトペをちょっと…勉強したいと思います！
Today, I'd like to learn a bit about Japanese onomatopoeia!
よろしくお願いします！
Nice to meet you all!
よろしくお願いします！じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Welcome! Next, Kobo-chan!
Water water water, Kobo Kanaeru at your service! Let me be your sun to shine your day!
こぼ・かなえる、雨使いです！今日はオノマトペ…
I'm Kobo Kanaeru, the shaman of rain! Today's onomatopoeia...
ガチだ！お願いします！頑張ろう！
I'll give it my all! Nice to meet you! Let me at it!
ワー！
Yay!
じゃあ続いてジジ！
Next up is Gigi!
こんばんは！ジジです！
Good evening! I'm Gigi!
日本語ちょっと上手じゃない…
My Japanese isn't that good yet...
オノマトペ、日本語頑張ります！
But I'll do my best with Japanese onomatopoeia!
ありがとう！頑張れー！
Thank you! Do your best!
じゃあ続いて、ほぼJPのベールズちゃん！
Next up, practically JP member Bae-chan!
いやいや！ホロライブEnglish、ハコス・ベールズです！
Hey now! I'm Hakos Baelz from Hololive English!
今日は翻訳担当で頑張りたいと思います！よろしくお願いします！
Today I'll do my best as the translator! Nice to meet you!
お願いします！
Welcome!
じゃあ最後、ラオラ！
And last but not least, Raora!
こんにちは！ラオラ・パンテーラです！
Hello! I'm Raora Panthera!
今日は絵を描いたり、日本語で話したり頑張りまーす！
Today I'll do my best drawing pictures and speaking Japanese!
はい、お願いします！
Great, welcome!
ということで、本日は皆さんにオノマトペクイズに答えてもらいます！
So today, everyone will be answering an onomatopoeia quiz!
日本独特の表現もたくさんあるんですが、頑張って答えてね。
There are many unique Japanese expressions, so do your best!
ぜひ日本に来る際は、いっぱい使っていただきたいなと思います！
I hope you can use them a lot when you visit Japan!
はい！ということで！
Alright then!
さっそく第1問行きましょう！
Let me present Question 1!
クエスチョン1！
Question 1!
このオノマトペは何を表しているでしょうか？「コケコッコー」
What does this onomatopoeia represent? "Kokekokko"
あ、What is this sound? コケコッコー
Ah, what is this sound? "Kokekokko"
Where do you hear this onomatopoeia from?
分からない！
I don't know!
ヒントは、動物の鳴き声ですね。なんの動物の鳴き声でしょう？
Here's a hint: it's an animal sound. What animal sound is it?
ペンがおかしいんです、私。なんで？
My pen... My pen is acting weird. Why?
え？おかしい？
Huh? It's weird?
コケコッコー
Cock-a-doodle-doo.
ペンがおかしい...あれ、なんでこんな...
My pen is weird... Huh, why is it like this?
描けるかな？
I wonder if I can draw?
あ、ちょっと待ってください。アプリ再起動します。
Ah, wait a second. I'm going to restart the app.
Should we draw?
You can do whatever.
I drew because I don't know what it is in Japanese.
I don't know the word!
なん、何ですか？
Wh-What is it?
描けるかな？
Can I draw it?
あ、描けます！あ、よかった！
Ah, I can draw! Ah, thank goodness!
よかったー。
Thank goodness!
声に出したらわかるかも。
Saying it out loud might help you figure it out.
遠い！
So far off!
大丈夫かい？
Are you okay?
コケコッコーですよ。
It's "cock-a-doodle-doo."
オッケー、じゃあ1人ずつ聞いていきましょう！
Okay, let's ask everyone one by one!
じゃあ、よっぴぴ！何だと思いますか？
Okay, Yoppipi! What do you think it is?
あ、チキンです！
Ah, chicken!
あ、チキン！はいはいはい、ニワトリね！
Ah, chicken! Right, right, right, a chicken!
はい、じゃあ、えー、コボちゃん！
Okay, next up, Kobo-chan!
Before I was thinking about frog,
but I think "kekokeko",
it sounds like Indonesian "kukuruyuk"!
So it's chicken!
あー、なるほど！
Ah, I see!
元々カエルだと思ってたんだけど、
She originally thought it was a frog,
インドネシアのオノマトペでも...
but even in Indonesian onomatopoeia...
オノマトペ...オノマトペ...
Onomatopoeia... Onomatopoeia...
ニワトリの声に似てるので、チキン！なるほどね。
...it sounds like a rooster's crow, so chicken! I see.
はい、じゃあジジ！
Okay, next up, Gigi!
「コケコッコー」、英語は Cock-a-doodle-doo!
"Kokekokko", in English it's "Cock-a-doodle-doo!"
Chicken!
Cock-a-doodle-doo！同じだね！
"Cock-a-doodle-doo!" So it's the same!
じゃあ、ベッちゃん！
Next, Bae-chan!
あ、僕もニワトリ、チキンだと思います！
Ah, I also think it's a chicken!
チキン！
Chicken!
じゃあ最後、ラーナ！
And lastly, Raora!
For me, it's like a bird that is screaming like...
"Coco!" Like "I'm here!" and...
...wants food in its mouth because maybe it's small, you know.
Wait, so what do you think it is?
Screaming bird... 叫ぶ鳥...
Screaming bird... Screaming bird...
叫ぶ鳥ね！
A screaming bird, huh?
A screaming bird, right!
お腹空いてる叫ぶ鳥ね！
A hungry screaming bird!
妖怪！
A monster!
じゃあ正解いきましょう！正解は...
Now then, let's reveal the answer! The answer is...
チキン、ニワトリでしたー！
Chicken, it was a chicken!
You got it!
やったー！
Yay!
まぁ、正解にしますか！叫ぶ鳥だもんね！
Well, let's count it as correct! It is a screaming bird after all!
鳥は鳥だからね！同じだからね！
A bird is a bird! It's basically the same thing!
素晴らしい！
Wonderful!
Everybody gets a point!
コケコッコー！
Cock-a-doodle-doo!
はい、じゃあ続いて第2問！こちらも動物の鳴き声でございます。
Alright, moving on to Question 2! This one is also an animal sound.
The second question is also the sound of an animal.
じゃあ第2問はこちら！ケロケロ！
Here is Question 2! "Kero kero!"
ケロケロ！
"Kero kero!"
Easy! Easy!
Easy, easy!
ケロケロ。
"Kero kero."
描けるかな？
Can you draw it?
ベーちゃん、それは...
Bae-chan, that is...
え？え？すごい！
Huh? Huh? Amazing!
何何何？
What is that?
Hey, my pen...
ケロケロケロケロ...
"Kero kero kero kero..."
可愛い！描けるかな？
Cute! Can you draw it?
ローラ、大丈夫？
Raora, are you okay?
あ、大丈夫。Okay, it's working. Thank you.
Ah, I'm okay. Okay, it's working. Thank you.
ベーちゃんのは何？え？
What is Bae-chan's drawing? Huh?
Hold on, I forgot what it looked like!
What are you drawing?
Why is she drawing herself?
I forgot what it looked like!
画伯！
Master artist!
It's like a chimera, you know? キメラみたい。
It's like a chimera, you know? It looks like a chimera.
キメラ...
Chimera...
キマイラなのやめて
Stop saying Chimera!
おいっちゃん、ちょっと1人ずつまた聞いていきますか。かわいいみんな。
Shall we ask each person one by one again? Everyone's so cute.
えー、じゃあ、イオフィ！
Uh, then, Iofi!
はい！
Yes!
カエル！Frogです。
Kaeru! It's frog.
ああ、Frog！ケロ、ケロケロでしょ？
Ah, frog! Kerokero, right?
その通り！はい！
Exactly! Yes!
じゃあ、続いて、こぼちゃん！
Next up, Kobo-chan!
あたしも、カエル... Frog, Frog, カエル、はい！ケロケロ！
Me too, frog... Frog, frog, kaeru, yes! Kerokero!
漢字で書いてる！すごーい！
She wrote it in kanji! Amazing!
まつりも書けないよ、カエル。
Even Matsuri can't write "frog" in kanji.
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Next up, Gigi!
はい！ケロケロ、ケロッピ！
Yes! Kerokero Keroppi!
あ、ケロケロケロッピ！おー！
Ah, Kerokero Keroppi! Oooh!
じゃあ、ベーちゃん！
Next, Bae-chan!
あ、カエルです。カエルかな？カエルです！
Ah, it's a frog. Is it a frog? It's a frog!
一瞬ずっとね、ネズミみたいに書いてたんだけど...
For a moment, she was drawing it like a mouse...
さっきね、カエル見たことないんで...
Actually, I've never seen a frog before...
画伯だ！
Quite the artist!
その隣の、えー、ラオーラ！めっちゃうまい！
Next to her, Raora! She's super good!
可愛い！可愛い！
So cute! So cute!
カエルですね？
It's a frog, right?
カエルです！
It's a frog!
じゃあ、ケロケロ、正解は... カエルでございます！
Now then, kerokero... The correct answer is... Frog!
正解！
Correct!
Easy! Easy! よかったー！
Easy! Easy! So glad!
日本語上手！日本語上手よ！
Your Japanese is so good! You guys are great at Japanese!
じゃあ続いていきますよ。続いては、えー、こちら！
Now then, let's move on. Next up is... this!
「馬の鳴き声は？」日本だと何と言うでしょう？
"What sound does a horse make?" What is it in Japan?
What sound does a horse make? Japanese onomatopoeia.
分からない！
I don't know!
なんて聞こえるかなー？
How does it sound to you guys?
イメージ、イメージして！
Imagine it, picture it!
It's alright Gigi, feel it from your heart!
You can do it!
1人ずつ鳴いてもらうからね！
Everyone will make their sound one by one!
She's gonna ask each of you to sound out the onomatopoeia that you have come up with.
オッケー？
Okay?
全然知らん...
I have no idea...
じゃあ、1人ずつ鳴いてもらえますか？
Now then, can everyone make their sound one by one?
じゃあ、イオフィから！イオフィの馬の鳴き声、お願いします！
Let's start with Iofi! Iofi, please give us your horse sound!
張り切っていこう！です！
It's "Let's go full power!"!
張り切っていこう？それ違くて！
"Let's go full power"? That's not it!
リアルな馬、これしかないのですよ！
For a real horse, this is all there is!
馬、これしか知らないのですよ！
This is all I know for a horse!
じゃあ続いて、こぼちゃん！
Next up, Kobo-chan!
ヒヒゥ、ヒヒゥ！
Hihu, hihu!
あれ？ヒフ？
Huh? Hihu?
I feel like that's a different sound!
別じゃん！
That's completely different!
オッケー、ヒフヒフね。
Okay, hihu hihu, right?
じゃあ、続いてジジ！
Next, Gigi!
Wild horse!
じゃあ、続いてベーちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
えーっと... うまー！うまー！
Um... U~ma~! U~ma~!
めっちゃ日本語喋るやん！
It speaks Japanese!
じゃあ、続いてラオーラ！
Next, Raora!
Okay, maybe something like...
リアル！
So realistic!
Turning into a horse!
You're a cat! What, that sounds like a horse!
めっちゃ似てた！
That was spot on!
正解は... 馬の鳴き声って何？
The correct answer is... Wait, what is a horse's sound?
ヒヒーン！でした！
It was "Hihin"!
ヒヒーン？
Hihin?
一番近かったらラオーラじゃないの？
If anyone was closest, wasn't it Raora?
ラオーラはリアルすぎたかな？
Was Raora too realistic?
Oh, there's an N at the end!
ヒ・ヒ・ン！
Hi-Hi-N!
Why do horses make that sound? Sounded like Michael Jackson!
both has Hihuu!
Both have Hihuu!
That's... that's it might count!
That's... that might count!
Oh yeah, Kobo does!
No, Hihuu too?
No Hihuu?
No Hihuu no?
Who know?
Who knows?
So it's no count?
So it doesn't count?
Ah, no count, sorry!
Ah, doesn't count, sorry!
可愛いけど...
It's cute, but...
はい、残念ながら不正解でございます。
Yes, unfortunately, that is incorrect.
では続いて...
Moving on to the next question...
今から言う言葉の意味を当ててください。
Please guess the meaning of the word I'm about to say.
じゃあ行きます。
Here we go.
What is the meaning of this?
「ぺこぺこだ～！」の意味は？
What is the meaning of "Peko-peko da~!"?
はいはいはい！
Yes, yes, yes!
What does "Peko-peko" mean?
あ、オッケー。
Ah, okay.
みんなスラスラと書いてくれている。
Everyone is writing it down smoothly.
オッケーかな？オッケーかな？
Are you ready? Is everyone done?
可愛いイラストが描かれている。
Cute illustrations are being drawn.
じゃあ聞いていきますか。
Alright, shall we check the answers?
じゃあ、ヨッピー！
First, Yoppy!
はい！
Yes!
Hungryです！食べたいです！プリン食べたいです！
It's hungry! I want to eat! I want to eat pudding!
Hungry！OK！
Hungry! Okay!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
はい！Peko-peko インドネシア語意味は「laper」です！
Yes! "Peko-peko" in Indonesian means "laper"!
「Laper」はどういう意味？
What does "laper" mean?
Laper is hungry!
Ah, hungry!
Hungryね、オッケー！
Hungry, okay!
じゃあ、ジジ！
Next, Gigi!
ジジ、顔だけしか描いてない。
Gigi only drew a face!
ジジ？
Gigi?
お腹すいた！
I'm hungry!
お腹すいたね！ジジ！
"I'm hungry"! Gigi!
可愛い！
So cute!
じゃあ続いて、ベイちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
はい！
Yes!
Hungryです！
It's hungry!
腹減った、オッケー！
"I'm hungry", okay!
じゃあ、ラオーラ！
Next, Raora!
Very hungry!
あ～！じゃあ全員同じだね！
Ah! So everyone got the same answer!
全員Hungry！
Everyone said hungry!
ということで...
And so...
全員正解～！
Everyone is correct~!
Yay!
イージー！イージー！
Easy! Easy!
上手上手！
Well done!
じゃあ続いて...、意味を当ててくださいね。
Moving on to the next one... Please guess the meaning.
Next one is also guess the meaning?
じゃあ行きます！
Here we go!
「チンしてね！」の意味は？
What is the meaning of "Chin shite ne!"?
Oh!
「チンしてね！」「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!" "Chin shite ne!"
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
可愛い可愛い！
So cute, so cute!
「チンしてね」
"Chin shite ne"
「チンしてね！」
"Chin shite ne!"
分かるかな？声に出したら分かるかもよ？
Do you know it? Maybe if you say it out loud you'll get it?
「チン」
"Chin"
可愛い！
Cute!
これじゃないの？
Isn't it this?
オッケーかな？
Are you ready?
ココな、ちょっと下にし...
Around here... I'll put it down a bit...
はい、じゃあ聞きますか。
Alright, shall we check the answers?
ヨッピー、どうでしょう？
Yoppy, what did you put?
はい！
Yes!
最初はちょっと doorbell だったんだけど...
At first I thought doorbell...
...あれピンポンだから、チンしたら Microwave...
...but that's ping-pong, so "chin" means microwave...
あ、Microwave！
Ah, microwave!
温める...
To warm up...
電子レンジ終わったら「チン」ってなるじゃない。
When the microwave finishes, it goes "chin".
なるほど！オッケー！
I see! Okay!
じゃあ、こぼちゃんは？
Then, how about Kobo-chan?
こぼちゃん...
Kobo-chan...
なんか「チン」は...
Somehow "chin" is...
ちょっと...
A bit...
いやいやいや！危険！
No no no! Dangerous!
そんなものみたい...
Looks like that kind of thing...
「チン」は...
"Chin" is...
Pee please? Pee please?
多分...わかんない！
I probably... don't know!
なるほど。じゃあ次行きますか？ジジ、ジジ！
I see. Shall we move to the next person? Zeta, Zeta!
わからなーい！
I don't know~!
チンやばい！やばい！
"Chin" is dangerous! It's dangerous!
チンやばい！No やばい！
"Chin" is dangerous! No, it's not!
じゃあ、ベーちゃんお願いたします！
Then Bae-chan, please go ahead!
はい。レンジのチンですね。温めてねっていうことで...
Yes. It's "chin" from a microwave. Meaning "warm it up"...
はいはいはい。じゃあ最後、ラオラ！
Right right right. And finally, Raora!
えー、わからなーい！わからなーい！
Uh, I don't know... I don't know!
Maybe... maybe something like...
Maybe when the glass, when you touch the glass...
ガラス？ああ～！チンって音？
Glass? Ah~! The "chin" clinking sound?
Not やばい. No やばいね. Not やばい.
Not bad. No, it's not bad. Not bad.
正解は... microwave! チン！
The correct answer is... microwave! "Chin"!
ご飯を温めてくださいっていう...
It means "Please warm up the food"...
電子レンジでご飯温めてって言いたい時に...
When you want to say "Warm up the food in the microwave"...
例えばご飯を置いておいて、後から帰ってきた人に「チンしてね」ってメモを残したりしますね。
For example, if you leave food out, you might leave a note for someone coming home later saying "Chin shite ne".
へぇ～！なるほど！
Whoa~! I see!
If someone says "Chin shite ne", it's like "Please warm it up for me".
Okay, so if you wanna... if you wanna say "Pee, please"...
How do you say that? I might need that one!
No pee! No pee!
じゃあ『Pee』はどう言ったらいいの？
Then how do you say "pee"?
オノマトペ？『Pee please』って何？
An onomatopoeia? What is "Pee please"?
『Pee』はおしっこ？
Does "Pee" mean urination?
あ、じゃあ『しー』とか『しゃー』とか...
Ah, then like "shh" or "shaa"...
しゃー please! しゃー please!
"Shaa" please! "Shaa" please!
しゃー、しーとか...
"Shaa", "shh", etc...
No no no! だめ、だめよ！
No no no! Don't say that!
すみません、しゃーお願い！
Excuse me, "shaa" please!
間違った日本語教えてる！
You're teaching wrong Japanese!
やばい！じゃあ次行きましょう！
Oh boy! Okay, let's move to the next one!
静まり返ったとき、めっちゃ静かなとき使うオノマトペは何でしょうか？
What is the onomatopoeia used when everything goes completely silent?
What's the onomatopoeia that they use when it goes really quiet?
Ah, maybe I remember!
あ、なんだっけ？静かなとき...
Ah, what was it again? When it's quiet...
Like when it goes really quiet all of a sudden, what's the onomatopoeia that they would use?
You can write it in romaji, or we can just sound it out.
漫画読んだらわかるかもね。漫画に書いてあることもあるかも。
You might know if you read manga. It's often written in manga.
It might be in manga that you've read before.
I don't know how to spell it... まあ、いいでしょう！
I don't know how to spell it... Well, it should be fine!
じゃあ聞いていきますね。イオフィから！
Okay, let me ask everyone. Starting with Iofi!
はい、『しーん』！シンプル！
Yes, "sheen"! Simple!
続いて、こぼちゃん！
Next up, Kobo-chan!
じゃあ、ジジ！
Next, Zeta!
しゃー！ Isn't that the pee?
"Shaa!" Isn't that the pee?
"Well, wouldn't it get quiet after you pee?"
じゃあ続いて、ベーちゃん！
Next up, Bae-chan!
いやー、忘れた... なんか... すー...
Ah, I forgot... like, "suu..."
あー、すー...
Ah, "suu..."
違う！
No!
すーはちょっと違うか...
"Suu" is a bit off...
しーになったか！
Did it become "shii"?
いや、どっちかと思ってたんだよね。
Yeah, I was wondering which one it was.
なるほど、なるほど。
I see, I see.
お、ミー？
Oh, me?
うん、Yes.
Yep, yes.
Yeah, I think it's "shii".
Like, I remember when I read some mangas, I might be wrong...
Maybe it's "shii".
うん、しー。オッケー、オッケー。
Mm, "shii". Okay, okay.
じゃあ正解に行きましょう！
Now, let's reveal the correct answer!
正解は... 「しー」でございます！
The correct answer is... "Shii"!
やっぱり！ベーちゃんとGigiが正解だね！
That's it! Bae-chan and Gigi got it right!
You were so close, Gigi!
Gigi was "Shii-n"?
しーん。
"Shii-n."
「ん」が必要ですね、コボちゃん。
You needed an "n", Kobo-chan.
あらららら！惜しい！
Oh dear! So close!
まあまあ、十分十分。
Well, close enough.
じじは絶対違うからね！
Jiji was definitely wrong!
「しゃー」は流石におしっこじゃないですか？
Isn't "shaa" the sound of peeing?
そう、さっきの「ピー」の音が...
Right, the "pee" sound earlier...
一応なんか理性的にも間違ってないと思うんすけどね。
Logically speaking, I don't think it's entirely wrong.
じじがおしっこした後にさ、静かになるじゃん。
After Jiji goes pee, it gets quiet, right?
そうそう！
Right, right!
だから「しゃー」！
That's why "shaa"!
I was explaining your logic.
Oh okay, thank you. So you're defending me?
Yeah, I'm defending you.
続いて行きましょう。続いて！
Let me move on to the next one. Next!
「とっても冷たい飲み物」を表すオノマトペは何でしょうか？
What is the onomatopoeia for an "extremely cold drink"?
What's the sound of an extremely cold drink?
飲み物...
Drink...
そう！
Yes!
あれ... あれだけど...
That... it's that, but...
何々に冷えたって言いますね。
You say cooled to "what-what".
Cold drink?
I only have one word in my head again!
How do I write it?
Cold drink... cold drink...
これもね、漫画に出てくるかもね。
This one might appear in manga too.
分からない！
I don't know!
Image! Image!
Sound! If I'm wrong, don't laugh!
Just do it! Just do it!
I'm scared!
It's okay!
じじがなんかヤバそうだ...
Jiji's answer looks kinda bad...
何を書こうとしてんの、じじ？大丈夫？
What are you trying to write, Jiji? Are you okay?
Is Jiji okay?
大丈夫、大丈夫！
I'm okay, I'm okay!
でも、あれかな？ビールとかに結構言うかな？
Maybe people say it a lot with beer?
Ah, it would be beer?
じゃあ、行きましょうか！
Shall we go then?
じゃあ、よぴぴ！
First, Yopipi!
はい！確か、キンキンなんとかの〜ホニャララです。
Yes! I think it's "kin-kin" something...
えーっと、この前スタジオで、ホロメンの誰かさんがマネージャーに「キンキンな飲み物が欲しいです」って言われてた。
Um, the other day at the studio, one of the Hololive members told their manager, "I want a kin-kin cold drink."
おー！なるほど！
Oh! I see!
そうそう。去年の夏くらいで、誰かさんちょっと忘れちゃったんだけど、スタジオで聞いたことがあります。
Yeah, around last summer, I forgot who, but I heard it at the studio.
キンキンね！オッケー！
Kin-kin! Okay!
じゃあ、コボ！
Next, Kobo!
So, I felt like after you drink a really cold drink, your head will hurt, and then you will say "Atata!".
冷たいもの飲んだ後さ、頭痛くなるんじゃないですか。
After drinking something cold, your head hurts, right?
あー、なるほど！
Ah, I see!
その時に「あたたたた！」って。
And at that time, "Atatatata!"
なるほどね！だからこそ「あたたた」と答えたわけですね。
I see! That's why you answered "atata".
じゃあ続いて、じじ！
Next, Jiji!
（ゴクゴク...）ぷはぁ！
*glug glug...* Ahhh!
寒い！
Cold!
寒いね！
Cold, right?
Yes!
寒い？
Cold?
寒い、うまい！
Cold, tasty!
寒い、うまい！かわいい！
Cold, tasty! Cute!
オッケー！寒い飲み物ね、オッケー！
Okay! Cold drink, okay!
はい。
Okay.
はい、OK。
Yeah, okay.
可愛い。
Cute.
じゃ、続いて、べーちゃん。
Next up, Bae.
なんか「き」から始まった気がした...忘れた。
I felt like it started with "ki"... but I forgot.
「き」から始まる...「き」なんちゃらかんちゃら「き」...
Starting with "ki"... "ki" something something "ki"...
「き」...「き」...「きん」で...
"ki"... "ki"... "kin-de"...
あ、「き」！「き」！OK、OK。
Ah, "ki"! "Ki"! Okay, okay.
「き」！
"Ki"!
じゃ、ラオラ！
Next, Raora!
あー、乾杯！
Ah, "Kanpai"!
あ、乾杯！乾杯！
Ah, cheers! Cheers!
Let's go!
Let's go, OK? 乾杯！
Let's go, okay? Cheers!
はい、じゃあ正解いきましょう。
Alright, let me reveal the correct answer.
正解は...「キンキンに冷えた飲み物」でございますので...
The correct answer is... "ice-cold drink," so...
「キンキン」ですね！
It's "Kin-kin"!
よっしゃー！すごい！
Awesome! Amazing!
ゆーだぁ、ありがとう誰かさんの...
You did it! Thank you to whoever...
「キン」かー！
It was "kin"!
はい、「キンキン」ね。
Yep, "kin-kin".
「キンキンに冷えてやがるよ」っていうセリフがアニメにもありますね！
There's a line in anime that goes, "It's freezin' cold!"
ほうほうほう。
Ho ho ho.
はい！じゃあ続いては...
Yes! Now for the next one...
えーっと...いきますか。続いてはこちら。
Um... shall we go? Next is this one.
よっしょ。「きらきら」...
Here we go. "Kirakira"...
星がきらきらしてる、みたいな「きらきら」の...
Like "twinkling" stars...
もっと強い表現！もっときらきら！
A stronger expression for "kirakira"! Even more sparkling!
もっと眩しい！
Even more dazzling!
ほうほうほう。どう表現するでしょうか？
Ooh. How would you express that?
So how would you describe something that, you know, you have "kirakira" to describe something that's sparkling...
...something that's even more bright and shiny? More than "kirakira".
あ、これは結構何パターンかある。
Ah, there are a few variations for this.
There's a couple of different variations.
あれ、なんだかあの、ほにゃららの...えっと、ポケモン思い出しちゃって...
Wait, somehow I remembered... um, Pokémon, and...
ポケモン！
Pokémon!
ポケモン？
Pokémon?
So, so like "kirakira" but a bit stronger, yeah, like more...
Like, with more punch. With more punch.
A level up "kirakira".
Level up "kirakira". Powerful "kirakira".
きらきら...
Kirakira...
分かるかな？
Do you know what it is?
可愛い。
Cute.
なんだろう...
I wonder what it is...
はい、はい、はい、はい。
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
書いてくれてる、まつりを。
She's drawing me!
可愛い。
Cute.
I'm bribing the judge.
ワイロ？
A bribe?
What?
I'm bribing the judge.
Why? She's trying to bribe the judge.
Why? I don't know the word.
なんかMCさんに賄賂を渡してます。
She's bribing the MC.
ん？わからん。何々？
Huh? What is it?
あの、知らないので、あの、MCに賄賂渡してます。
Since I don't know it, I'm bribing the MC.
賄賂？！
Bribe?!
ああ！そういうこと？！じゃあヒントね、ヒント！
Ah, is that it?! Okay, here's a hint!
ヒントは、ホロライブメンバーの曲の歌詞に入ってますね。
The hint is: it's in a Hololive member's song lyrics.
もっと言うと、ねねちの...ねねちのあの曲！
More specifically, Nenechi's... Nenechi's song!
Oh, it's in the lyrics of a Hololive member's song! Nenechi's song!
に、入ってる。
It's in that song.
あとは「きらきら」の進化。「きらきら」をパワーアップさせた感じかな？
Also, it's an evolution of "kirakira". Like a powered-up "kirakira".
おー！が、ヒント！どうでしょうか？
Ooh! That's the hint! How about it?
オッケー？賄賂オッケー？
Okay? Bribe accepted?
賄賂は...これ賄賂くれたの誰？
Who gave the bribe?
誰がくれたの？
Who gave it?
ジジ？ジジだな！
Gigi? It's Gigi!
ジジじゃ...賄賂として「Very cute voice, please, Matsuri-oneesan」OK？
Gigi, as a bribe, "Very cute voice, please, Matsuri-oneesan," okay?
はい！あの絵が賄賂なんですよ！
Yes! That drawing is the bribe!
あ、そういうことね！可愛い！
Ah, I see! Cute!
期待、期待...まつりお姉さん...きらきら...
Looking forward to it... Matsuri-oneesan... sparkling...
大好き！
I love you!
きゃー！
Kyaa!
可愛い！
So cute!
あ、ジジ、あの..."Your name is a hint".
Ah, Gigi, "Your name is a hint".
Your name is a hint? My name is a hint?! It is!
あー！あれね！
Ah! That one!
で、ねねちの曲にも入ってるよと。
And it's also in Nenechi's song.
オッケー
Okay.
いけるかな？
Is it working?
じゃあ聞いていこう
Let's hear from everyone.
じゃあ、よぴぴから
Alright, starting with Yopi!
はい、えーっと、キラーンとか、キラキラとか、そういう？
Yes, um... like "kiran" or "kirakira", things like that?
かなと思ってて。でも今思ってたらあれだなと思ってて。
...is what I thought. But now I'm having second thoughts.
お！変えますか？
Oh! Do you want to change it?
いや、大丈夫です！
No, it's fine!
なんか、そう、そのキラキラもっと強いのが、なんかいつも太陽？
Well, yeah, something stronger than "kirakira"... like the sun?
太陽、だから太陽がピピィーってなってるじゃないですか。
Like, the sun radiating beam-like rays, right?
太陽によく使われるのかな？
Is it often used for the sun?
なるほど、はいはいはいはい
I see. Right, right, right.
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
かわいい
So cute.
'Cuz I heard someone saying...
...Pokemon?
So I think, like...
Pika Pika!
確かに強い！確かに強い！ピカピカ！
It's definitely strong! "Pika Pika" is strong!
ピカピカ強い！Strong Pika Pika!
Pika Pika is strong! Strong Pika Pika!
じゃあ続いてジジ！
Next up, Gigi!
Giga Giga!
はーはいはい、ギラギラ、オッケー？
Ah, okay, okay, "Giragira", right?
オッケーオッケー、じゃあべーちゃんいきましょう
Okay, okay, let's go to Bae-chan!
あ、僕もピカピカだと思ってた。
Ah, I also thought it was "Pika Pika".
ピカピカね！オッケー！
"Pika Pika", okay!
じゃあ、ラオラ！
Next, Raora!
Same for me, I heard about Pokemon!
About Pikachu...
ポケモンヒントだからね！なるほどなるほど！
Since Pokemon was the hint! I see, I see!
オッケー！じゃあ正解いきましょう！
Okay! Let's reveal the correct answer!
正解は... ギラギラ！で、ジジ正解！
The answer is... "Giragira"! Gigi got it right!
ギラギラ！
Giragira!
天才じゃん！買収されたわ！
She's a genius! She must have bribed someone!
ピカピカちょっと惜しくて、それがね、ビカビカとかだったら正解。
"Pika Pika" was close. If it were "Bikabika", that would be correct.
あー、ビカビカ！
Ah, Bikabika!
もっと眩しいね。
It's even more dazzling.
ビカビカの方が強いんだ！
"Bikabika" is stronger!
そう！ピカピカはまあ、キラキラと同じくらい。
Yes! "Pika Pika" is about the same level as "Kirakira".
ちょっと弱いかな？ビカビカ、ギラギラ。
A bit weaker maybe? "Bikabika" and "Giragira" are stronger.
So Pika Pika is on the same level as Kirakira.
いつも聞いてるのが「ギラギラ太陽なんとか」っていう…
I often hear phrases like "giragira sun something"...
そうそうそう！
Right, right, right!
メンバーのね、ギラファもね、同じ感じで明るい、眩しい、みたいな言葉かなと思いますね。
Like our member fan meeting "Girafa", it's used similarly for bright and dazzling things.
I see, I see, I see. All you need to know...
Bribing works!
Bribing works? I mean I could bribe... Yeah, it works.
続いていきましょう！
Let's move on!
続いて同じ感じでございますけども...
Next up, in a similar format...
心臓のこの音、「どきどき」をもっと強く表現すると？
How would you express the sound of a heartbeat, "dokidoki", more strongly?
Stronger "dokidoki"!
Bigger than dokidoki?
これもね、何パターンかあるから、合ってたら大丈夫で。
There are a few possible answers, so as long as it fits, it's fine.
何パターンかあるんだろうな。はい。
There are probably a few answers. Okay.
まあ2つ、3つくらい表現はあるかな？
There are maybe two or three ways to express it.
ドクン？
"Dokun"?
どきどき...
Dokidoki...
どきどき... 何だろうな...
Dokidoki... I wonder what...
もっと強く、強く...
More strongly, strongly...
ちなみに弱くすると...
By the way, if you make it weaker...
弱くすると、「トクン」とかですね。
If you make it weaker, it's "tokun" or something.
お！オッケー！
Oh! Okay!
これもちょっとヒントになるかな？
Maybe that serves as a hint?
トクン、トクン... どきどき...
Tokun, tokun... dokidoki...
Another like similar level is "tokun, tokun", so that's a hint. So you want something stronger than "tokun, tokun".
Another similar level is "tokun, tokun", so that's a hint. So you want something stronger than "tokun, tokun".
これもちょっと可愛い声で「まつりお姉さん」って言ったらもっとヒントくれます？
If I ask in a cute voice, "Matsuri-oneesan", will you give me another hint?
ヒント？！
A hint?!
ヒントくださーい！
Give me a hint, please!
可愛く「まつりお姉さん」って言ったらもっとヒントくれます？
If I cutely say "Matsuri-oneesan", will you give another hint?
あ、オッケー！オッケー！
Ah, okay! Okay!
いいよ！どうぞ！
Sure! Go ahead!
え？い、いいんですか？ / いいよ！ / え、いいんですか？ / うん！
Huh? Is it okay? / Sure! / Really, is it okay? / Yep!
えーちゃんちょっとあのヒントお願いしまーす
A-chan, can we get a hint, please?
えーヒントはないにゃー
Eh? There are no hints, nya~
1つだけでいいからお姉ちゃん！
Just one is fine, big sister!
1つだけね
Just one, okay?
めっちゃこれヒントだけどー
This is a huge hint, but...
まあ...強調するのに日本では...
Well... to emphasize it, in Japan...
結構ちっちゃい「つ」を入れたりとか
people often add a small "tsu", or...
あー！あー！あとは...そうですね
Ah! Ah! Also... let's see.
あと言葉を変えるんだったら、あの...なんだろうな
Also, if you were to change the word itself, well... what would it be?
大きな...大きな音っぽいというか...
Something that sounds like a bigger sound...
まあ、音もね、大きそうだけどね。
Well, the sound seems bigger too, right?
はい、まそんな感じですかね。
Yeah, something like that!
はい！ありがとうレタス！
Okay! Thank you lettuce!
うわっ！よし！
Whoa! Alright!
OK, OK, OK...
You could totally bribe the MC!
OK, OK, OK... じゃあ聞いていきましょう！
OK, OK, OK... Let's hear your answers!
Why did you bribe the MC?!
じゃあ、えー、イオフィからいきますか？
So, shall we start with Iofi?
はい！
Yes!
ドックンです！はい、ドックン！
It's "Dokkun"! Yes, "Dokkun"!
ドックン！ドックン！ドックン！ドックン！
Dokkun! Dokkun! Dokkun! Dokkun!
あい！
Yes!
ほうー！
Oh~!
えー、じゃあ、コボ！
Okay, next up, Kobo!
Uh I remembered to mock Zeta about a part of her original song lyrics,
it's "babu babu", but it's actually "bagu bagu" or "bagu bagu"
Yeah, something like that.
あー、バグバグ！ふんふんふん。
Ah, "bagu bagu"! Mm-hmm.
じゃあ続いて、ゼータ！
Okay, next, Zeta!
ウマ娘！
Umamusume!
ドキドキドキ！ドキュン！ドキュン！
Doki doki doki! Dokyun! Dokyun!
あー、ドキュンもある！
Ah, "Dokyun" is one too!
はいはいはい！なるほど！確かに！
Right, right, right! I see! Indeed!
じゃあ、ベーちゃん！
Next, Bae-chan!
いや、もうドキドキをもっと強くして、もはや心臓破裂...
Well, making "dokidoki" even stronger, it's pretty much a heart burst...
ドド ド ド ド ド ド...
Do-do-do-do-do-do-do...
はい！
Okay!
じゃあ、ラオラ！
Next, Raora!
Ah... It's "Bakun bakun!"
あー、バックンバックンか！
Ah, "Bakun bakun"!
I was listening recently, so...
あー、なるほどねー！
Ah, I see!
結構みんな違うんだけどー
Everyone's answers are quite different, but...
じゃあ正解...正解者は...
well, the correct... the correct ones are...
これね、全員正解でいいかなと思います！
I think everyone gets a pass for this one!
Oh, everyone's right! Yeah!
いろんな表現があって...
There are so many different expressions...
まあ「ドッキン」とか「ドックンドックン」とか...
Like "dokkin", "dokkun dokkun"...
「ドキドキ」「ドッキドキ」とか...
"dokidoki", "dokkidoki"...
「ドドドド」も強そう！
"Do-do-do-do" sounds intense too!
死んでるよ！
You'd be dead!
緊張してる時とかに「ドドドド」って...
Like when you're super nervous, your heart goes "do-do-do-do"...
はい、ということで全員正解！素晴らしい！
So, everyone is correct! Amazing!
Yay! やっ たー！
Yay! We did it!
みんなすごい！みんな上手！
Everyone's so good at this!
今度は...今からとあるサウンドを聴いてもらいます。
Next... you're going to listen to a certain sound effect.
チャンネルにボイスを貼りますので...
I'll post the audio clip in the channel...
これ何と言っているでしょうかという問題でございますね。
The question is, "What sound does this cicada make?"
なんと聞こえるか...
What does it sound like to you?
今からセミの鳴き声を送ります。
I'll send the sound of a cicada crying right now.
何と言っているでしょうか、セミは？
What is the cicada saying?
All right, she sent a little voice clip. What is this cicada saying?
じゃあ、リスナーさんにも聴かせます。こちらです。
Okay, let's play it for the viewers as well. Here it is.
Oh, so we have to come up with an onomatopoeia!
From listening to it...
It's in the chat, in the chat.
これは何と鳴いているでしょうか？
How is it crying?
なるほど、なるほど！
I see, I see!
So what is that sound that the cicada is making?
日本人だったらね、絶対に分かるね。
If you're Japanese, you'd definitely know this.
How do you pronounce it?
Cicada?
It's cicada. I always pronounce it "Chichada"!
Chichada?! Enchilada!
Enchilada!
I thought it was "Chichada"!
これは何かな？
What is this one?
What does it look like? Cicada?
あー、分かるかな？
Ah, will they figure it out?
It has big wings... Yeah!
I've never seen it before.
I've seen it all the time in summer.
Cicadas, like, everywhere.
They fall and they cannot fly again.
これ分かったらJPやね
If you know this, you're definitely Japanese.
さすがに
For sure.
本物の蝉見たことないんです
I've never seen a real cicada before.
え？いないの？
Eh? You don't have them?
いるとは思うんだけど、声は聞こえるけど姿が...どこにいるのか分かんない
I think they exist, and I can hear them, but I don't know where they are.
そうなんだ。子供の頃蝉捕りとかしないの？
Oh really? Didn't you catch cicadas as a kid?
ない
No.
あれは多分、結構日本文化的な...
That's probably quite a Japanese culture thing...
へえ！そうなんだ！
Oh! Is that so?!
ないない
Nope, never.
じゃあ蝉の種類とか言われても分かんないのか
So you wouldn't know even if we talked about types of cicadas.
分かんないです！全員蝉だもん！
I don't know! They're all just cicadas to me!
確かに！全員蝉だもん！
True! They're all just cicadas!
へえー、そうなんだ
Huh, I see.
Have any of you guys caught cicadas before?
Ever caught one before?
No.
I got one in my balcony.
I got one on my balcony.
え？
Eh?
Your balcony?!
It was huge! It was super big! And super loud!
バルコニー... ベランダ、ベランダにいた？
Balcony... Veranda, it was on your veranda?
そんなに大きいの？蝉って
Are cicadas really that big?
結構デカいよ。よくいるよ、その辺に死んでるのとか
They're pretty big. You often see dead ones lying around.
Big bug!
コウモリくらいのかな？
Maybe about the size of a bat?
大丈夫じゃない。何回も聞いていいよ
No, you're not okay. You can listen to it again.
大丈夫じゃない！
I'm not okay!
Can I have a hint? ヒントお願い！
Can I have a hint? Please give us a hint!
ヒントは... 「ショワショワ」言ってるのは無視していい
The hint is... you can ignore the buzzing sound in the background.
大きい、低めの音の蝉さんはなんて言ってるかだね
Listen to what the lower-pitched, big cicada sound is saying.
Take the sound of the lower-sounding note. Ignore the "showa showa" in the background.
困ってるね
They look troubled.
オッケー！じゃあ行きましょう！イオフィぴから！
Okay! Let me go through everyone, starting with Iofi-pi!
はい！みーみー！
Yes! Mii-mii!
じゃあこぼちゃん！
Next, Kobo-chan!
チー！チー！
Chi-! Chi-!
可愛い！
Cute!
はい、じゃあアーニャ！
Okay, next Anya!
ジジは「ジー、ジー、ジー！」
"Jiji" is "Jii, jii, jii!"
ジジの鳴き声！
An old man's sound!
じゃあ続いてべちゃん！
Next up, Ollie-chan!
ウイーン！ウイーン！
Ween! Ween!
オッケー。じゃあラスト、りーな！
Okay. And last, Reine!
クリ、クリ、クリ...
Kuri, kuri, kuri...
じゃあ正解行きましょう！正解は...
Alright, let's reveal the correct answer! The answer is...
ミーン、ミーン、ミーン、ミーンで...
"Miin, miin, miin, miin", so...
イオフィぴ正解！
Iofi-pi is correct!
It doesn't sound like "miin" at all!
えー、聞こえないんだよね。「M」の音なくない？
Eh? You can't hear it? Isn't there no 'M' sound?
There's no M sound!
この蝉の名前がそもそも「ミンミンゼミ」という名前の蝉でね
The name of this cicada is actually "Minminzemi" in the first place.
「ミーン、ミーン」って日本人には聞こえてますね
Japanese people hear it as "miin, miin".
じゃあ続いて、ネクスト蝉行きますよ
Alright, moving on to the next cicada!
ネクスト蝉？！
Next cicada?!
ワンモア蝉行きます
One more cicada coming up.
蝉２、こちらです。じゃあ皆さんにも聞かせます
Cicada #2 is this one. Let me play it for everyone.
What is that?!
何これ？！
What is this?!
何？！
What?!
めっちゃ聞こえますね！日本人にはめちゃめちゃ...
I can hear it so clearly! To Japanese people, it's super...
Where does this sound come from?
I don't know! What the heck?!
蝉バージョン２ですよ
It's Cicada Version 2.
分かるかな？
Can you figure it out?
蝉２ね
Cicada 2.
ヒントお願いします！
Hint please!
ヒント？！
A hint?!
ヒントは…
The hint is...
あの、タタタタターン、タタタタターンっていうのが鳴き声
Um, the sound it makes is like "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan, ta-ta-ta-ta-taan".
タタタタターン、タタタタターン…
"Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan, ta-ta-ta-ta-taan..."
が、日本人には…タタタタターン
To Japanese people, "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan"...
だから、まあ、5文字くらいかな？
So, it's about five characters long, I guess?
え？5？
Huh? Five?
Like like sound, the sound that makes that pattern.
Like the sound that makes that pattern.
A pattern?
ヒント難しいね、文字数は。
It's hard to give a hint for this one.
ちょっとタタタタターンもオノマトペと言われたら、もうごめんなさい。それは…
If you ask if "ta-ta-ta-ta-taan" is an onomatopoeia, I'm sorry. That's...
えー、むずっ…
Huh, that's hard...
もうタタタタタタターンしか思い出せない。
Now I can only think of "ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-taan".
タタタタタタタ…
"Ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta-ta..."
んー、Wait...
Hm, wait...
7文字か！
Ah, 7 characters!
嘘でしょ、もう言ってるようなもん。
No way! That's basically giving it away!
まあ、伸ばし棒が入ります、あと。最後の方に。
Well, it also includes a long vowel mark near the end.
え！？ There is an elongated... Is it 7 characters?
Huh!? There is an elongated... Is it 7 characters?
伸ばすと7文字ですね。
With the long vowel mark, it's 7 characters.
ええー！？
Eeh!?
あれろ、あげバーナーガストか。
What's that? Age-bana-gasuto?
難しいね。
This is hard!
この声、リズム自体はわかるんだけど、どう書いていいのかわからない。
I can picture the rhythm of the sound, but I don't know how to write it down.
落ち着くね。タタタタターン、落ち着かないね。
It's relaxing. "Ta-ta-ta-ta-taan"—wait, isn't it unrelaxing?
落ち着く？
Relaxing?
この声を聞くと落ち着きますよ。「夏だな」って。
When you hear this sound, it feels relaxing. Like, "Ah, summer is here."
えー？
Huh?
That sound is relaxing to Japanese people?
ええー？
Eeh?
落ち着くよね？
It's relaxing, right?
OK、じゃあ行きましょうか。イオピぴから。
Okay, let's go! Starting with Iofi-pi!
いや、「ククククク」じゃないですか？セミバージョン2。
Isn't it "kukukuku"? Cicada Version 2!
セミバージョン2！ククククク？
Cicada Version 2! "Kukukuku"?
クククククで！
"Kukukuku" it is!
オーケー、オーケー。じゃあ、こぼちゃん！
Okay, okay! Next, Kobo-chan!
こぼ…
Kobo...
Um, so...
The previous one was "min-min", right?
Uh-huh.
And, uh, I heard...
this is more than "min-min", so it's...
a mating call like "meng-meng"!
ちょっと待って！
Wait a second!
そもそも、Why did you write "Mating Call"?
First of all, why did you write "Mating Call"?
えっと、求愛の泣き声メンメンです。
Um, the mating call is "meng-meng".
あー、求愛の泣き声なんだよね、実際。
Ah, it actually IS a mating call!
あ、そうなの！？
Oh, really!?
Why don't you write it IS a mating call?
セミのオスがメスが来た時言ってる時の声だから、そこは正しい！
That's the sound male cicadas make when a female approaches, so that part is correct!
正しい！求愛のね！
Correct! It's a courtship call!
Oh my god!
でもメンメンが正しいかどうかね。
But we'll see if "meng-meng" is correct or not.
Ah, so "meng-meng", okay.
じゃあ、ジジ！
Next, Gigi!
Um, "ji", "ji", "ji"...
上手！
So good!
オーケー、「ジ」オッケーね！
Okay, "ji" is okay!
じゃあ、べーちゃん！
Next, Bae-chan!
え？なんか…
Huh? Something like...
ポコポコピカ！ポコポコピカ！
"Poko-poko-pika! Poko-poko-pika!"
ポケモンみたいだけど。
Sounds like a Pokémon though!
ポケモンみたい！オーケー、ポコポコピカね！
Like a Pokémon! Okay, "Poko-poko-pika"!
じゃあ、ラオーラ！
Next, Raora!
Ah, you know, peanut... It's a cricket!
You know, it's a cricket!
And a cricket sounds like "purin purin purin purin"!
And a cricket sounds like "purin-purin-purin-purin"!
プリンプリン！かわいい！
"Purin-purin"! Cute!
オーケー、オーケー！
Okay, okay!
じゃあ、いきます！こちらの泣き声は…
Okay, here we go! This sound is...
ツクツクボウシでございます！
Tsukutsukuboshi!
ええーー！？
Ehhhh!?
なぜ？なんで？Why?
Why? How? Why?
ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！
Tsukutsukuboshi! Tsukutsukuboshi!
ツクツクボウシ！
Tsukutsukuboshi!
So I should do this if I want to mating call someone?
ちょっと待って、実際…
Wait a second, actually...
Oh my god! Like that?
ツクツクボウシ！ツクツクボウシ！
Tsukutsukuboshi! Tsukutsukuboshi!
ヤバいやばいやばい！
Crazy! This is crazy!
Yeah, buy! Yeah, buy! Shut up, please!
Yabai! Yabai! Shut up, please!
学んでしまった！ Shut up! お願い、Shut up!
I learned something new! Shut up! Please, shut up!
まあ、ツクツクボウシかツクツクホウシ、どちらでもOK。
Well, either "Tsukutsukuboshi" or "Tsukutsukuhoshi" is fine.
どちらでもOKとなっております。
Either one is acceptable.
ちょっとね、これセミは難しいですね。
Cicada sounds are pretty difficult, huh?
Wow!
セミの種類とかは関係ないんですか？あ、これはツクツクボウシっていうセミの鳴き声ですね、今のは。
Does the species of cicada not matter? Ah, that was the sound of a cicada called Tsukutsukuboshi just now.
種類もツクツクボウシっていう名前のセミ。
The species name itself is Tsukutsukuboshi cicada.
ちなみに他にも、さっきのがミンミンゼミだったでしょ？
By the way, earlier we had the Minmin cicada, right?
アブラゼミっていうのが、ジジジジジッて鳴くのがアブラゼミ。
And Aburazemi is the one that goes "ji-ji-ji-ji-ji".
セミだったり...
Like cicadas...
あ、アブラゼミ！
Ah, Aburazemi!
日本人だったら蝉の声を聞くだけで何の蝉かわかります。
If you're Japanese, just hearing a cicada tells you what kind it is.
え！？ Wow!
What?! Wow!
They can differentiate what kind of cicada it is depending on what it sounds like!
There's different enchiladas...
There are different enchiladas...
Yeah, so what we heard were two different enchiladas, Gigi.
So you're saying that there is an enchilada that says "ji-ji"? Yeah!
え、3種類って何の名前だったっけ？
Wait, what were the names of the three types again?
ええと、ジジジはアブラゼミですね。
Um, "ji-ji-ji" is the Aburazemi, right?
アブラゼミ！ はい。 Aburazemi... Aburazemi... Yes!
Aburazemi! Yes. Aburazemi... Aburazemi... Yes!
Large brown cicada... Large brown cicada, yes!
なるほど！ なるほど！
I see! I see!
続いてラスト問題！
Moving on to the last question!
これはめっちゃちょっと... ジャパニーズすぎる、難しいと思うんですけど...
This one is a bit... too Japanese, I think it's gonna be tough, but...
これ解けたら、もういつ日本に来ても戦えます！
If you get this right, you can survive anytime you come to Japan!
日本には独特な、これにしか使わないオノマトペがあります。
Japan has a unique onomatopoeia used only for this.
桃が川から流れてくるオノマトペは何でしょう？
What is the onomatopoeia for a peach floating down a river?
What is the onomatopoeia for when a peach comes floating down the river?
桃太郎読んだことないんだったら、できないじゃないですか！ これ桃太郎！
If they haven't read Momotaro, they won't be able to answer! This is Momotaro!
これ分かったら、もう日本に来ていただいていつでも...
If they get this right, they can come to Japan anytime...
So what is the sound that a peach makes when it flows down the river?
字が汚いよ！ ええと...
Your handwriting is messy! Um...
Is it folklore? Yeah, you know Momotaro, the Peach Boy? Yeah, it's very specific.
I can't... We gotta guess! We gotta guess!
桃にしか使わないですね。りんごとかが代わりに流れてても使わない。
It's only used for peaches. Even if an apple floats down instead, it's not used.
Only used for peaches? It's only peaches? My god.
No, I'm sure this is gonna be really weird. 桃太郎読んだことないんだったら、分かんないやつ...
No, I'm sure this is gonna be really weird. If you haven't read Momotaro, you won't know it...
桃太郎一回読んだんだよね？ お、じゃあ分かるじゃん。
You read Momotaro once, right? Oh, then you should know it.
Maybe I know that legend point... oh, 'cause I watched...
So if you read the actual book, it's written in the book. So if you haven't read it, you probably don't know.
え、そんなことあるの！？
Eh, really?!
なんか確か前にあの... 雑談配信でこれのことちょっと語った気がする。
I feel like I talked about this during a previous chat stream...
そうなんだ！ そう。「なんでこうなったの？」って言われたら分かんないけど...
Oh, really?! Yeah. If asked "Why did it become like this?", I wouldn't know, but...
すごい！ でも話すんだ。 昔話ね。
Wow! But you talk about it. Fairy tales, right.
何だっけ？ これはね... 知らないと本当に当てられないと思うけど...
What was it? I think unless you know it, you really can't guess it...
日本人だったら、ちっちゃい子からおじいちゃんおばあちゃんまでみんな分かるからね。
If you're Japanese, everyone from little kids to grandparents knows it.
桃の川流れてる音なんだって。
They say it's the sound of a peach floating down a river.
はい。じゃあ行きましょうか、最終問題。じゃあ、ゆぴぴどうでしょう？
Okay. Let's move to the final question. Yupipi, what's your answer?
はい！ 「どんぶらこ」です。 はい、「どんぶらこ」！ 「どんぶらこ」、オッケー！
Yes! It's "Donburako". Yes, "Donburako"! "Donburako", okay!
じゃあ、こぼちゃん！ お尻？ 「もんごもんご」！
Next, Kobo-chan! Butt? "Mongo mongo"!
「もんごもんご」！？ 「もんごもんご」！
"Mongo mongo"?! "Mongo mongo"!
かわいい！ お尻みたいに流れてるの？ うん！
Cute! Floating like a butt? Yeah!
じゃあ、ジジ！ If I saw a huge peach floating in the water...
Okay, Gigi! If I saw a huge peach floating in the water...
and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, and it was, you know, like a peach, I would go "Ah, wow! Dekai!"
and it was like a really big peach and it was huge, I would go "Ah, wow! Huge!"
Like... めちゃめちゃJuicy! Dekai!
Like... Super juicy! Huge!
おばあちゃんが「Juicy! Dekai!」って言うの？ 「Dekai!」ってなっちゃうの？
Would the grandma say "Juicy! Huge!"? Would she just go "Huge!"?
「お尻 dekai!」「お尻 dekai!」 Oh my! 「桃 dekai!」
"Butt huge!" "Butt huge!" Oh my! "Peach huge!"
じゃあ、ビッちゃん！
Next up, Bijou-chan!
世長... 「ドンプシャー！」っていう...
Yonaga... "Donpusha!" or something...
「ドンプシャー！」 水のね！ 水の音ね！
"Donpusha!" Water sound, right! Water sound!
はい。じゃあ、続いてラオーラ！
Okay. Next up, Raora!
Um, maybe it's "Puka-puka"? Ah, "Puka-puka"! "Puka-puka"! Cute!
オッケー。じゃあ、正解行きましょう！
Okay. Then let's reveal the correct answer!
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこですね。
It's "donburako, donburako," right?
Oh my god! Oh my god!
なぜです？なぜかは、そうやって本に書いてあるからね。
Why, you ask? Because that's what's written in books.
へぇ〜
Huh~
理由はない。え、ちなみに理由はない。
There's no reason. By the way, there's no reason.
理由はない？
No reason?
ない、ない、ないよ。
Nope, none at all.
そう聴こえるのかな？
Maybe that's what it sounds like?
で、あれだね。
And then...
「ぷかぷか」は浮いているもの。水に浮いてたら「ぷかぷか」で合ってる。
"Puka-puka" is for floating things. If it's floating on water, "puka-puka" is correct.
Oh, so if it's floating in the water, it would be "puka-puka".
But 'cause it's coming down the stream, it's flowing down the stream...
どんぶらこ、どんぶらこ。
Donburako, donburako.
そう、桃が川から流れてくるときは「どんぶらこ」ですね。
Right, when a peach floats down a river, it's "donburako."
And it has to be a peach? If it's an apple or anything else, it's not...?
リンゴだったら「ぷかぷか」。
If it's an apple, it's "puka-puka."
Oh my god!
桃だけ？！ Peach only?!
Only peaches?! Peach only?!
Oh my god!
ということでね、皆さんも…
So anyway, everyone...
Why Japan?! Why Japan?!
難しいね、オノマトペ。
Onomatopoeia is difficult, isn't it?
でも可愛かったのでね。
But it was cute.
あ、ちなみにオノマトペではないんですけど、今日みんなに覚えていってほしい言葉があります。
Ah, by the way, it's not an onomatopoeia, but there's a phrase I want everyone to learn today.
Oh, there's a phrase she wants us to learn.
「全然分からない」っていうのを日本語では「ちんぷんかんぷん」って言いますね。
To say "I don't understand at all," in Japanese we say "chinpun kanpun."
ちんぷんかんぷん！可愛い！
Chinpun kanpun! How cute!
ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chinpun kanpun!
そうそうそう。「全然分からない」…
Right, right. When you have no idea...
When you have no idea of anything, this is the onomatopoeia you use.
ちんぷんかんぷん！ちんぷんかんぷん！
Chinpun kanpun! Chinpun kanpun!
I like that! I'm very scared of you using this phrase.
Every time someone asks me something, "chinpun kanpun!"
I'm just scared of you forgetting what the full phrase is...
ちん…
Chin...
残酷な言葉ですよ、「チン」ツンカンプン…
That becomes a dirty word! "Chin"-tsun-kanpun...
はい、ということで…
Yes, so...
Scared of using "chinpun kanpun"...
全部覚えられないとき…
When you can't remember everything...
The "chin" part that you can't remember is scary!
覚えて、「ちんぷんかんぷん」。漢字もあるからね、「珍紛漢紛」って。
Remember "chinpun kanpun." It even has kanji, "珍紛漢紛."
え、漢字もあるの？そう、漢字もあります。
Eh, kanji too?! Yes, there are kanji for it.
カタカナやひらがなで言うことが多いけど、ちゃんと漢字がある。
Though it's often written in katakana or hiragana, it actually has kanji.
漢字が？そう、漢字があるんです。
Kanji?! Yes, it has kanji.
むず！
So hard!
読めん！コメントで書いてくれてるけど、それが「珍紛漢紛」ですね。
Can't read it! They're writing it in the comments, that's "chinpun kanpun."
珍しい何々… ちんぷんかんぷん！
"Rare" something something... Chinpun kanpun!
でもめちゃめちゃ可愛いから、「日本語ちんぷんかんぷんです」って言ったらもうオッケー。
But it's super cute, so if you say "My Japanese is chinpun kanpun," you're all set!
すべて解決。 Okay! Okay! Again!
Everything's solved. Okay! Okay! Again!
はい、ということで… なるほど〜！
All right, so... I see~!
There's one onomatopoeia that Okayu-senpai taught me once.
おかゆ先輩に教えてくれたオノマトペあります。何ですか？
There's an onomatopoeia Okayu-senpai taught me. What is it?
え、ぶるんぶるんです！
Um, it's "burun-burun"!
ぶるんぶるん？ブロンブロン？
Burun-burun? Buron-buron?
おっぱいを揺らすときの音。
The sound of shaking breasts.
Oh my! ぶらんぶらん…
Oh my! Buran-buran...
ぶるんぶるん… ぼいんぼいん…
Burun-burun... Boin-boin...
ぼいんぼいんもある！合ってる、両方おっぱい。
There's "boin-boin" too! Both are correct for breasts.
で、もっと大きなおっぱいだと「ばいんばいん」になります。
And for even bigger breasts, it becomes "bain-bain."
Bain-bain! Bain-bain!
もっと大きいおっぱいは「ばいんばいん」！
Even bigger breasts are "bain-bain"!
それ以上大きい胸はないですか？それ以上大きいのはないね。ばいんばいんが一番大きい。
Are there no bigger breasts than that? There's nothing bigger than that. "Bain-bain" is the biggest.
はい、ということで。 JAPAN WHY?! 最後これかよ！
All right, so... JAPAN WHY?! Ending on this?!
今日の優勝者 一応発表しますか？
Shall we announce today's winner?
今日はですね イオフィが優勝でございます！
Today, Iofi is our winner!
半分以上正解して...
She got more than half of them right...
天才だ！ さすがでございます！
She's a genius! As expected!
いやいや 日本語上手！
No way... Your Japanese is so good!
でもね 他のメンバーも半分は正解してますから 素晴らしいでございます！
But you know, the other members got half of them right too, which is wonderful!
わー！ やったー！
Yay! Awesome!
ということで 皆さん本日もありがとうございました！
So then, thank you everyone so much for watching today!
チャンネル登録もね... ありがとうございました！
And for subscribing... Thank you so much!
チャンネル登録の方も ポチッとお願いますね
Be sure to click that subscribe button, too!
お願いします！ お願いします！
Please do! Please do!
ということで 最後はバイバイで終わっていきますよ せーの！
All right, let's finish off with a "bye-bye"! Ready, set...
バイバーイ！
Bye-bye!
ちんぽんかんぽん！ ちんぽんかんぽん！
Chimpon kampon! Chimpon kampon!
ぶろんぶろん！ バイバイ！
Vroom vroom! Bye-bye!